# MARÍA VALENTINA GARCÍA-ALVARADO

Bogotá, Colombia. (+57) 3134059779 mv.garcia@uniandes.edu.co

Fifth year Physics undergraduate student and fourth year Engineering student at Universidad de los Andes in Colombia. Beginner researcher in computational Cosmology and Star Formation. Interested in acquiring knowledge on Astronomy, Astrophysics and Computer Science. Looking forward to pursuing a PhD in Astrophysics focusing my research on Galaxy formation and evolution, Star formation or Cosmology.

#### **EDUCATION**

JANUARY 2018 – CURRENTLY FIFTH YEAR (EXPECTED GRADUATION DATE: JUNE 2023) BACHELOR OF SCIENCE: PHYSICS

UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

JANUARY 2019 – CURRENTLY FOURTH YEAR (EXPECTED GRADUATION DATE: JUNE 2023) BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING: SYSTEMS AND COMPUTING ENGINEERING

UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

JUNE 2020 – TODAY
MINOR IN ASTRONOMY

UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

#### **SCHOOLS**

**SEPTEMBER 2020** 

**SUMMER SCHOOL ON GALAXIES AND COSMOLOGY** 

INSTITUT TEKNOLOGI BANDUNG, INDONESIA Link to the school: <a href="https://www.as.itb.ac.id/ssgc2020/">https://www.as.itb.ac.id/ssgc2020/</a>

**NOVEMBER 2020** 

**ASTRONOMY TWINNING PROGRAM** 

LEIDEN OBSERVATORY AND UNIVERSITY OF ANTIOQUIA

Link to the school: <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/astrotwincolo/home">https://sites.google.com/site/astrotwincolo/home</a>

**JUNE 2021** 

**ESCAPE SUMMER SCHOOL** 

EUROPEAN SCIENCE CLUSTER OF ASTRONOMY & PARTICLE PHYSICS ESFRI RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURES

Link to the school: <a href="https://indico.in2p3.fr/event/20306/">https://indico.in2p3.fr/event/20306/</a>

**JUNE - JULY 2021** 

#### MEXICAN ASTROCOSMOSTATISTICS SCHOOL

UNIVERSITY OF GUANAJUATO, MEXICO

Link to the school: <a href="http://fisica.ugto.mx/~events/macss/">http://fisica.ugto.mx/~events/macss/</a>

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2018 - 2020

UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

ADVISOR: Jaime E. Forero-Romero, PhD

## The cosmic web through the lens of graph entropy

An analysis of the cosmic web using properties of graphs. Applied the beta-skeleton graph on simulated dark matter halos and measured its graph entropy. We found the correlation between the entropy and quantities such as the cosmological parameters.

#### **JUNE - SEPTEMBER 2021**

CHALMERS ASTROPHYSICS & SPACE SCIENCE SUMMER (CASSUM)

ADVISORS: Jonathan Tan, PhD. Chia-Jung Hsu, MsC.

## Structural analysis of massive protoclusters formed from cloud collisions

An study of the structure of evolving massive protoclusters using properties of graphs to determine properties of the parent molecular cloud. Applied dendrogram to identify protostellar cores at different stages of evolution and compute its Minimum Spanning Tree. We computed quantities such as the mass segregation of the cluster and analyzed the spatial distribution of the cores.

Research program link: <a href="http://cosmicorigins.space/cassum21">http://cosmicorigins.space/cassum21</a>

#### 2021

UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

ADVISOR: Jaime E. Forero-Romero, PhD

Analyzing spectra from DESI using UMAP

Finding anomalous spectra coming from DESI to detect failures on the instrument (specifically, physical defects in some CCDs), using Umap. Umap is a dimension reduction technique that has shown to be effective in classifying multidimensional objects into groups. Spectra coming from a CCD with failures are grouped differently.

## **PUBLICATIONS**

The cosmic web through the lens of graph entropy. M. V. García-Alvarado, X.-D Li and J. E.

Forero-Romero, MNRAS: Letters, 498, L115, 2020.

Link to the publication: https://doi.org/10.1093/mnrasl/slaa145

Structural analysis of massive protoclusters. **M. V. García-Alvarado**, Jonathan Tan, PhD. Chia-Jung Hsu, in prep.

#### CONFERENCES

**NOVEMBER 2019** 

## LATIN AMERICAN IAU MEETING – ANTOFAGASTA, CHILE

TALK: BETA-SKELETON FOR THE ANALYISIS OF THE LARGE SCALE STRUCTURE OF THE UNIVERSE

Link to the event: http://www.sochias.cl/larim2019/

#### OCTOBER 2019

## CONGRESO COLOMBIANO DE ASTRONOMÍA - MEDELLÍN, COLOMBIA

TALK: CONSTRAINING COSMOLOGICAL PARAMETERS WITH THE BETA-SKELETON OF

THE COSMIC WEB

Link to the event: https://planetariomedellin.org/COCOA2019

#### **JANUARY 2022**

## ORIGINS WORKSHOP – SALT LAKE CITY, UTAH.

TALK (VIDEOCONFERENCE): STRUCTURAL ANALYSIS OF MASSIVE PROTOCLUSTERS

Link to the event: <a href="http://cosmicorigins.space/originsslc">http://cosmicorigins.space/originsslc</a>

#### OCTOBER 2020

## SEMINARIO DE ASTRONOMÍA, UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES – BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

TALK (VIDEOCONFERENCE): FINDING QSO PAIRS

#### **AUGUST 2021**

## SEMINARIO DE ASTRONOMÍA, UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

TALK (VIDEOCONFERENCE): STRUCTURAL ANALYSIS OF MASSIVE PROTOCLUSTERS

#### **SEPTEMBER 2020**

## COSMOLOGÍA EN COLOMBIA - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

TALK (VIDEOCONFERENCE): THE COSMIC WEB THROUGH THE LENS OF GRAPH

**ENTROPY** 

Link to the event: https://indico.cern.ch/event/926040/

## **MARCH 2019**

## COSMOLOGÍA EN COLOMBIA - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

TALK: CONSTRAINING COSMOLOGICAL PARAMETERS WITH THE BETA-SKELETON OF

THE COSMIC WEB

Link to the event: <a href="https://indico.cern.ch/event/799097/">https://indico.cern.ch/event/799097/</a>

## **DECEMBER 2020**

## ICTP-SAIFR LATIN AMERICAN WORKSHOP ON OBSERVATIONAL COSMOLOGY – SÃO PAULO, BRAZIL

POSTER (VIDEOCONFERENCE): THE COSMIC WEB THROUGH THE LENS OF GRAPH ENTROPY

Link to the event: <a href="https://www.ictp-saifr.org/south-american-workshop-on-cosmology-in-the-lsst-era/">https://www.ictp-saifr.org/south-american-workshop-on-cosmology-in-the-lsst-era/</a>

## **OBSERVING EXPERIENCE**

#### **DECEMBER 2021**

## **SUPPORT OBSERVER, DESI**

Supported DESI observations for four consecutive nights.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### **AUGUST 2019 - DECEMBER 2020**

TUTOR, UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

Tutored undergraduate engineering and science students in Python programming skills.

#### **AUGUST 2020 – DECEMBER 2020**

**GRADER.** UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

Graded exams from a basic physics class.

## AUGUST 2021 - DECEMBER 2021

TUTOR, UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

Tutored undergraduate engineering and science students in basic Physics topics (Basic Mechanics, Electrodynamics, Thermodynamics).

## **MENTORSHIP**

#### **FEBRUARY 2021 – JULY 2021**

PENTA BY SHE SPEAKS SCIENCE

Participant of the mentorship program supported by the University of Cambridge and the IAU. After a competitive selection, I was one of the 33 women selected from all around the world to mentor a girl and be mentored by another woman in STEM. This program aims to create a community of empowered women by giving advice and supporting each other.

Link to the program: <a href="https://www.shespeaksscience.com/penta/">https://www.shespeaksscience.com/penta/</a>

## **FEBRUARY 2021 – MAY 2021**

MENTOR IN COMPAS PROGRAM AT UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

Mentor at the mentorship program for students at their first semester.

## **SKILLS**

- Proficient at Python and Java programming.
- Proficient at managing data bases with SQL.
- Wide experience using LaTeX.
- Experience on processing of N body simulations.
- Experience with version controlling using Git.
- Manage the basics of Bash.